Finding Aid for Gunnar Birkerts papers 1930-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Project Files
  - Central Market Master Plan, Riga, Latvia, 1995
    - Architectural Drawings
      - "Central Market Master Plan for Restoration, Rehabilitation and Expansion of the Market District.", Design presentation booklet, including photographic prints, site plans and conceptual drawings, 11x17 inches, undated (Map-case 11, Folder 4)
  - AirTouch Cellular Communications Tower at Domino's Farms, Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1995
    - Project Files
      - Correspondence, 1995 (Box 10)
      - Newspaper Article, 1997 (Box 10)
    - Architectural Drawings
      - Conceptual Sketches., Undated (Map-case 11, Folder 4)
        - [Elevation], untitled, Blue ink sketch on white tracing paper, initialed, 18x17-1/4 inches (Map-case 11, Folder 4)
      - Schematic Design Drawings
        - [Elevation], untitled, undated; 01/01/1995; Two pencil and red pencil drawings on vellum, 21x15 & 16x15 inches, one initialed (Map-case 11, Folder 4)
Related Material
Researchers are encouraged to access both the Gunnar Birkerts and Associates Collection and the Gunnar Birkerts Collection at the Bentley Historical Library. When studied together, they give the richest possible picture of the architectural design process, from the ecstatic moment of the conception of a building through the meticulous development of schematic design, design development and construction drawings. The Gunnar Birkerts and Associates Collection is distinguished from the Gunnar Birkerts Collection by its aggregation of 69 linear feet of the firm's textual records and 7158 drawings which document the design process for 14 of Birkerts' most critically acclaimed buildings. A separate finding aid for the Gunnar Birkerts and Associates Collection can be electronically accessed at www.umich.edu/~bhl/. This should be consulted by those interested in studying the evolution of the design process for the following buildings, which were selected because they represent the significance and diversity of the architect's work:
Haley Funeral Home (1960-1961)
University Reformed Church (1960-1964)
Freeman Residence (1964-1966)
Lincoln Elementary School (1965-1967)
Tougaloo College Master Plan, Library and Dormitories (1965-1972)
Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis (1967-1973)
Duluth Public Library (1969-1980)
S.U.N.Y., Purchase College, Dance Instructional Facility (1970-1976)
Corning Municipal Fire Station (1973-1974)
Calvary Baptist Church (1974-1977)
University of Michigan Law Library Addition (1974-1981)
Corning Museum of Glass (1976-1980)
Ferguson Residence (1980-1983)
St. Peter's Lutheran Church (1981-1988)
Bibliography
Researchers are also referred to a number of books about the work and career of Gunnar Birkerts housed at the Bentley Historical Library:
Birkerts, Gunnar.Buildings, Projects and Thoughts, 1960-1985. Ann Arbor, Michigan: The University of Michigan, College of Architecture and Urban Planning, 1985.
Birkerts, Gunnar.Process and Expression in Architectural Form. Norman, Oklahoma: University of Oklahoma Press, 1994.
Bugbee, Gordon P.Domino's Mansion: Thomas Monaghan, Gunnar Birkerts and the Spirit of Frank Lloyd Wright. Troy, Michigan: Planning Research Organization For A Better Environment (PROBE) Press, 1988.
Kaiser, Kay.The Architecture of Gunnar Birkerts. Washington, D.C.: The American Institute of Architects Press, 1989.
Kaiser, Kay. "Profile: Gunnar Birkerts."World Architecture, No. 36, 23-53, 1995
Marlin, William.GA Architect: Gunnar Birkerts and Associates. Tokyo: A.D.A. EDITA Tokyo Co., Ltd., 1982.
The finding aid for Gunnar Birkerts & Associates records includes a comprehensive bibliography which was provided by Gunnar Birkerts and Associates, listing all books and journal articles written about the architect, his firm and his buildings. These references provide critical analysis of most of his projects and will enhance the scholar's understanding of Birkerts' work.